<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<protocol name="playos_shell_v1">
  <copyright>
    Copyright (c) 2026 PlayOS Foundation

    Permission is hereby granted, free of charge, to any person obtaining a
    copy of this software and associated documentation files (the "Software"),
    to deal in the Software without restriction, including without limitation
    the rights to use, copy, modify, merge, publish, distribute, sublicense,
    and/or sell copies of the Software, and to permit persons to whom the
    Software is furnished to do so, subject to the following conditions:

    The above copyright notice and this permission notice shall be included
    in all copies or substantial portions of the Software.
  </copyright>

  <description summary="PlayOS shell surface role">
    A global interface that a PlayOS shell client binds to in order to
    declare its surface as the shell surface.

    The compositor uses this role to:
    - keep the shell alive as the background client,
    - restore the shell to the foreground when a game exits,
    - route Home-button events to terminate the active game,
    - maintain shell focus when no game is active.

    A client that does not bind this protocol will not be treated as the
    shell. Only one shell surface may be active at a time; binding a
    new surface replaces the previous shell.
  </description>

  <interface name="playos_shell_v1" version="1">
    <description summary="PlayOS shell surface role">
      A global interface for declaring a surface as the PlayOS Shell.
      The client binds to this global and calls set_shell_surface to
      associate one of its wl_surfaces with the shell role.
    </description>

    <request name="set_shell_surface">
      <description summary="declare a surface as the shell">
        Associate the given wl_surface with the shell role. The surface
        must already have (or will be given) the xdg_toplevel role.

        If a shell surface was previously declared, the old association
        is replaced and the previous shell toplevel is closed.

        A client may call this request only once per playos_shell_v1
        object. Calling it more than once is a protocol error.
      </description>
      <arg name="surface" type="object" interface="wl_surface"
           summary="the surface to assign the shell role to"/>
    </request>
  </interface>
</protocol>
