<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<protocol name="playos_game_v1">
  <copyright>
    Copyright (c) 2026 PlayOS Foundation

    Permission is hereby granted, free of charge, to any person obtaining a
    copy of this software and associated documentation files (the "Software"),
    to deal in the Software without restriction, including without limitation
    the rights to use, copy, modify, merge, publish, distribute, sublicense,
    and/or sell copies of the Software, and to permit persons to whom the
    Software is furnished to do so, subject to the following conditions:

    The above copyright notice and this permission notice shall be included
    in all copies or substantial portions of the Software.
  </copyright>

  <description summary="PlayOS game surface role">
    A global interface that a PlayOS game client binds to in order to
    declare its surface as the active game surface.

    The compositor uses this role to:
    - present the game in the foreground, above the shell,
    - route gameplay input to the game,
    - target the game when the Home button is pressed,
    - track game lifecycle for crash recovery.

    A client that does not bind this protocol will not receive gameplay
    focus. Only one game surface may be active at a time; binding a new
    surface replaces the previous game.
  </description>

  <interface name="playos_game_v1" version="1">
    <description summary="PlayOS game surface role">
      A global interface for declaring a surface as the active game.
      The client binds to this global and calls set_game_surface to
      associate one of its wl_surfaces with the game role.
    </description>

    <request name="set_game_surface">
      <description summary="declare a surface as the active game">
        Associate the given wl_surface with the game role. The surface
        must already have (or will be given) the xdg_toplevel role.

        If a game surface was previously declared, the old association
        is replaced and the previous game toplevel is closed.

        A client may call this request only once per playos_game_v1
        object. Calling it more than once is a protocol error.
      </description>
      <arg name="surface" type="object" interface="wl_surface"
           summary="the surface to assign the game role to"/>
    </request>
  </interface>
</protocol>
