<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<protocol name="playos_compositor_control_v1">
  <copyright>
    Copyright (c) 2026 PlayOS Foundation

    Permission is hereby granted, free of charge, to any person obtaining a
    copy of this software and associated documentation files (the "Software"),
    to deal in the Software without restriction, including without limitation
    the rights to use, copy, modify, merge, publish, distribute, sublicense,
    and/or sell copies of the Software, and to permit persons to whom the
    Software is furnished to do so, subject to the following conditions:

    The above copyright notice and this permission notice shall be included
    in all copies or substantial portions of the Software.
  </copyright>

  <description summary="PlayOS compositor control interface">
    Control interface for runtime services (playos-sessiond) to manage
    the compositor's presentation state. The runtime binds as a Wayland
    client and uses this protocol to request shell/game activation and
    receive lifecycle events.

    This is the Stage 2 IPC channel between the compositor and the
    runtime. Future stages will add overlay control, display-mode
    management, and presentation-state queries.
  </description>

  <interface name="playos_compositor_control_v1" version="1">
    <description summary="compositor control interface">
      A global interface for runtime-to-compositor control. Only one
      client may bind this interface at a time (the runtime). If a
      second client binds, the compositor will close the connection.

      Requests flow from the runtime to the compositor; events flow
      from the compositor to the runtime.
    </description>

    <request name="activate_shell">
      <description summary="close the active game and show the shell">
        Close the currently active game toplevel (if any) and bring
        the shell to the foreground. If no game is active, this is
        a no-op — the shell (if alive) remains in the foreground.

        This is equivalent to pressing the Home button.
      </description>
    </request>

    <event name="game_closed">
      <description summary="active game toplevel was destroyed">
        Sent when the active game toplevel is destroyed, whether by
        Home-button press, client disconnect, crash, or an explicit
        activate_shell request. The runtime should use this event to
        clean up process state and prepare for the next game launch.
      </description>
    </event>

    <event name="shell_closed">
      <description summary="shell toplevel was destroyed">
        Sent when the shell toplevel is destroyed. The runtime should
        restart the shell process when it receives this event.
      </description>
    </event>
  </interface>
</protocol>
